Finding Aid for the John Allison Benjamin Papers Biomed.0001
UCLA Library Special Collections
John Allison Benjamin papers
1925-1994
UCLA Library Special Collections
Biomed.0001
12.0 Linear Feet (10 cartons + 1 box: 10 storage cartons (12 1/2" x 10" x 16 1/2"): containers #1 - #10; 1 storage box (21" x3" x17"): container #11)
10 cartons + 1 box (12 linear ft.): 10 storage cartons (12 1/2" x 10" x 16 1/2"): containers #1 - #10; 1 storage box (21" x3" x17"): container #11
Conditions Governing Access
Portions of this collection are restricted. Folders marked "restricted" are unavailable.
In order to access materials that are protected under HIPAA (Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act) or for which there is sensitive health information, please submit a research protocol to Library Special Collections at speccoll@library.ucla.edu.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942357433606533
Biography
John Allison Benjamin (1906-Dec. 25, 1992), M.D., urologist, surgeon, scientist, teacher, collector of a treasure trove of rare books in the history of medicine and science, and generous benefactor, was a self-made man. Innate capability and a driving work ethic propelled him, not privileged birth or extraordinary opportunities. His intellectual drive and ambition led to contacts with men who would act as role models, mentors, and friends until he had achieved his own renown, when he in turn became a gifted and conscientious teacher and mentor.
Dr. Benjamin had wide-ranging curiosity, interests, and achievements. First he was, according to many statements and hints to be found in these papers, a superb and warmly caring clinician; his patients seem to have adored him, and younger urologists gave credit to his example long after leaving his wards. Second, he was a very good scientist, doing animal experiments to further basic urological understanding; his work in developing cinematography of the urinary tract, in both dogs and humans, was pioneering. And third, with little background except some school Latin, through sheer perseverance and many hours of self study, he became a good historian of urology and a superb book collector, fashioning a well-focused collection of rare medical & scientific works that became renowned in its field.
The professional recognition Dr. Benjamin received as clinician and scientist is well documented in the papers. He was a founder and president of the Society for Pediatric Urology, prominent in the American Urological Association and several of its regional sections, editorial board member of the Journal of Urology, author of many chapters and many, many papers in the literature of urology, including its history. As a book collector and benefactor he was also widely hailed. In 1964 Dr. Benjamin presented his library of over 700 volumes of classics in medicine and science to the Biomedical Library of the University of California, Los Angeles, and for many years thereafter he added priceless volumes to that collection.
John A. Benjamin was born in Salmon, Idaho, the oldest of six children in a poor and troubled household. He attended the small local schools and escaped as soon as he was ready for college, to the home of relatives in Santa Ana, California. Commuting by streetcar, he entered UCLA at its old downtown location, a member of the first class to graduate, with a B.A. in Zoology, from the new Westwood campus in 1930. Then he entered The Johns Hopkins University Medical School, maintaining himself with money he had saved from working during college, further part-time jobs, and help from his So. California relatives. He received the M.D. degree in 1934.
Urology was already his primary field of interest. During the summer of 1933 he was awarded a student fellowship by the Rockefeller Foundation, International Health Division, to study venereal disease in the Southern U.S. After graduation he interned in genitourinary surgery and gynecology with Dr. Hugh Young in Baltimore for a year, and spent the following year as general surgery intern with Dr. T.F. Riggs of Pierre, So. Dakota. Then followed urological residency training at the University of Rochester Medical Center, from 1936 to 1939.
After completion of his residency, Dr. Benjamin returned to Los Angeles to join the urology practice of Dr. E. Belt, where he stayed for two years. Elmer Belt served as a major role model -- not only as clinician and educator, but he also transferred his abiding fascination with the history of medicine and the collection of rare medical books to his young colleague. Dr. Benjamin himself stated that he owed his collecting drive to Dr. Belt's example.
Dr. Benjamin next shifted to private practice in Portland, Oregon, from 1941 to 1942. But then he received an invitation, eagerly accepted, to join the faculty of the University of Rochester School of Medicine as Assistant Professor of Urological Surgery. At this time Dr. Benjamin married his second wife, Mae McElman Benjamin, with whom he celebrated his 50th wedding anniversary a few months before his death. He continued as a full-time faculty member until 1957, then as part-time clinical professor until his retirement in 1971; during all this time he had a busy private practice.
The Benjamins moved back to So. California after retirement, but Dr. Benjamin soon grew restless with inactivity. Fortunately a professional friend grabbed the opportunity to recruit him, and in 1971 Dr. Benjamin joined the Department of Urology of the Southern California Permanente Medical Group, where he practiced for seventeen more years.
Dr. Benjamin was survived by his wife, Mae, his four children and six grandchildren.
Scope and Content
The bulk of this collection documents Dr. Benjamin's research and clinical activities, the research covering the urogenital systems of both humans and animals and historical/bibliographic topics. The papers mostly span the years from 1930 to 1988 --years of professional education and working life -- with a few earlier and later items. There are also translations, photocopies and microfilm of early classic publications, dating as far back as the 15th century. Perhaps one-eighth of all the material is concerned with the John A. Benjamin Collection of Medical History, including the correspondence with rare book dealers and with UCLA librarians from which a separate provenance database has been constructed. A smaller percentage of the material can be considered personal, concerning Dr. Benjamin's background, family, and friends.
The provenance database contains information on author, title, place and date of publication, name of the source supplying the work, the date and price of purchase, and location of the pertinent documents within the collection, for each volume for which such information could be found. This information is available from the History & Special Collections Division, UCLA Biomedical Library.
In addition to the paper documents, the collection contains well over 500 photographs, over 600 35 mm slides, over 200 lantern slides, eleven motion pictures, nine film strips, and numerous x-rays. There is also a 45 min. videotape of an interview with Dr. Benjamin sponsored by the American Urological Association which gives a wonderful capsule biography and insight into the man.
Dr. Benjamin apparently made an effort to save all his papers, including multiple drafts and multiple copies of drafts of publications under development. Some of the material is handwritten, often on small cards or scraps of paper, and his handwriting was typical of the physician writing stereotype -- i.e., illegible. If they carried no additional notes or editing, multiple copies of typescripts were discarded by the processor; the same held for multiple copies of reprints. Duplication was also avoided as much as possible among the non-print materials, although there is still some overlap of images between photographs, 35 mm slides, and lantern slides.
Organization and Arrangement
The materials were arranged by the processor into seven series:
I. Early Study and Research (7 folders, 1930-1936)
II. Research, Teaching, Patient Care -- Urogenital System (92 folders, 1939-1991)
III. Research -- Historical & bibliographic (48 folders, 1940-1991)
IV. Supporting Research Materials (73 folders, 1934-1991)
V. The John A. Benjamin Collection of Rare Medical Books (38 folders, 1942-1993)
VI. Personal Materials (22 folders, 1925-1992)
VII. Nonprint Materials (ca. 500 photographs, ca. 50 x-rays, 11 motion pictures, 14 film strips, 660 35 mm slides, 206 glass lantern slides, 1 phonograph record, 1 videocassette, & 2 tie tacks, no dates). Series and subseries are arranged chronologically. The contents of boxes 1-8 and 11 are identified as "folders"; of box 9 as "film" or "film strip," etc.; of box 10 as "item." The Table of Contents preceding this section affords an overview of series and subseries.
Abbreviations
JAB John Allison Benjamin
MTG Martha Teach Gnudi
KESD Katharine E.S. Donahue
JZ Jake Zeitlin
F Folder
I Item
FS film strip
Access Points
Benjamin, John A. (John Allison), 1906-; Urology.; Urology--history.; Urogenital System.; History of Medicine.; Book Collecting.; O'Malley, Charles Donald.; Gnudi, Martha Teach, 1908-; Belt, Elmer, 1893-1980.; Young, Hugh, 1870-1945.; Goodwin, Willard E.; Steele, Victoria.; Donahue, Katharine E. S.; John A. Benjamin Collection of Medical History.; American Urological Association.
Container List
- I. EARLY STUDY AND RESEARCH
  - Medical school, 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    handwritten & typed class & reading notes; notice of award of M.D. degree; for certificate, see Box 9-F4
  - Operative surgery, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    descriptions of five operations and autopsies performed on dogs by JAB
  - Impressions, by J. Allison Benjamin, Jr., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    report by JAB on summer study under auspices of International Health Division, The Rockefeller Foundation, while a medical student at Johns Hopkins University; two typescripts of successive drafts, edited
  - "The third ventricle: conformation of the floor and its relation to the meninges", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    reprint of article by Curt P. Richter and JAB, Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry, 31:1026-1037, May 1934; mounted illustrations
  - "Ligation of the common bile duct in the rat: anatomic and behavior- istic effects", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    reprint of article by Curt P. Richter and JAB, Archives of Pathology, 18:817-826, Dec 1934; used and unused illustrations
  - "The occurrence of pigment in the pars intermedia and pars tuberalis of the hypophysis, and in the hypophyseal leptomeninges of the rat (domestic and wild)", 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    typed draft and reprint of an article by JAB, Anatomical Record, 61(3):331-339, Feb. 1935; handwritten notes; two reprints, on menin- ges and pigmentation in rat hypophysis, from 1932; photographs mounted as three plates, plus two unmounted photographs; issue no. 248 of The Wistar Institute Bibliographic Service Advance Abstract Sheet, Oct. 1934, which includes an abstract of JAB's article
  - "Appendicitis: acute and acute-perforated", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    subtitle: "Brief report of 300 cases with a consideration of the prone position to facilitate drainage," by Theodore F. Riggs, J.F. Blackman, H.C. Harrill, JAB; reprint of a presentation to the Annual Meeting of the Western Surgical Association, published in the Transactions of the Western Surgical Association, 46:287-295, 1936
- II. RESEARCH, TEACHING, PATIENT CARE -- UROGENITAL SYSTEM
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1940-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    a mixture of professional and more personal letters; see also Box 7- F27 for overlapping material
  - Office files, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    folder designation by JAB; contains summaries of patients' operative histories; correspondence; notes for a lecture; notifications from the states of Colorado & Oregon to JAB granting him Basic Science Certificates [RESTRICTED]
  - Letters of recommendation, 1976-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    written by JAB
  - Results obtained with sulfanilamide in the treatment of gonococcic and other urinary tract infections, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    typescript of a paper by Donald Forbes Marshall and JAB
  - "Total prostatectomy in the rabbit and intra-ocular transplantation of prostatic tissue: anatomic-surgical procedure", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    reprint & mounted illustrations of article by JAB, Elmer Belt, & Boris Krichesky, Journal of Urology, 44(1):109-115, July 1940
  - "Some side effects of sulfanilamide and its derivatives. Report of five cases", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    reprint, drafts, & illustration of article by JAB and Elmer Belt, The Urologic and Cutaneous Review, 44(12):786-790, Dec. 1940; correspondence
  - "The value of stereoscopic pneumographic studies in the diagnosis and localization of renal and ureteral calculi", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    reprint & draft of article by W.W. Scott & JAB, New York State Journal of Medicine, 40(4):276-283, Feb. 1940; notes; numerous translations from the F rench & German, including articles by Von Lichtenberg, and by Rosenstein on a method of peri-renal insufflation, 1922-1923; extensive typed bibliography on pyelography, peri-renal insufflation, & related topics
  - "Endocrinologic studies on the prostate gland in the male rabbit. I.The response of intra-ocular prostatic implants to testosterone propionate and to castration in completely prostatectomized animals", 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    many draft versions plus a reprint of the paper by Boris Krichesky, JAB, Elmer Belt, and Monte Schwartz, eventually published in Journal of Urology, 46:303-318, 1941; notes, correspondence, and several short background papers on various aspects of prostate structure and function; for E. Belt's presentation to Urologists' Correspondence Club, 5/5/41, see letter from JAB to MTG, 8/26/66, in Box 6-F20; see also Box 1-F16 & F32
  - "Response of intraocular prostatic implants in rabbit to gonadotropic hormone administration", 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    reprint, typescript, & illustrations of article by B. Rosenberg, B. Krichesky and JAB, Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 48:263-265, 1941; see also Box 1-F15 & F32
  - Description of operations, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    notes on two procedures on a named patient, dictated by JAB, surgeon, at White Memorial Hospital, Los Angeles [RESTRICTED]
  - Stilbesterol-prostate-rabbit-Krichesky, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    heading from original folder, In JAB's handwriting; notes, translations from the German, correspondence with Dr. B. Bickel at the Army Medical Library; see also Box 1-F15 & F16
  - Papers on hormones and cancer, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    notes on three dog experiments, "estrogens & carcinogenic studies," 1942; extensive annotated bibliographic notes; three reprints by various authors
  - "Vasitis nodosa: a new clinical entity simulating tuberculosis of the vas deferens", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    reprint & drafts of article by JAB, Thomas D. Robertson, John G. Cheetham, Journal of Urology, 49(4):575-582, Apr. 1943; correspondence; mounted illustrations
  - "Inactivation of endogenous androgens by the liver in rabbits", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    reprint & draft of an article by B. Krichesky, JAB, & C. Slater, Endocrinology, 32(4):345-350, Apr. 1943; correspondence
  - "Effect of gonadotropic hormones on intraocular prostatic implants in the male rabbit", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    reprint of an article by B. Krichesky, JAB, & B. Rosenberg, Endocrinology, 33(1):32-38, Jul. 1943
  - Development of opaque & contrast pyelography mediums, 1943 [no date- early '40s?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    extensive notes, bibliographic entries, beginning drafts for an article; circular for drug "Diodrast" and reprint of article by Albert M. Meads, "Intravenous vs. retrograde pyelography," The Urologic and Cutaneous Review, 44(12), 1940, which was sent by a colleague (signature unreadable); overlaps materials in Box 1-F24 and Box 5-F10
  - Information on contrast media, [1945?} (Box 1, Folder 24)
    photostats of two articles, and two typed pages plus short bibliography titled "Radio contrast medium 'Roche' "; all enclosed in mailing envolope from Hoffmann-La Roche, 1945; overlaps materials in Box 1-F23 and Box 5-F10
  - "Quantitative microchemical and spectrographic data on renal calculi and their relation to infection", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    reprint, drafts, & illustrations of article by H.E. Thompson, L.T. Steadman, JAB, W.W. Scott, Journal of Urology, 51(3):259-271, Mar. 1944; extensive notes; two reprints by Charles Pierre Mathé et al.
  - "Anatomical study and clinical consideration of the fasciae limiting urinary extravasation from the penile urethra", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    reprint & some illustrations of article by Charles E. Tobin and JAB, Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 79:195-204, Aug. 1944; see also Box 4-F7
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1941-1960 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    bibliography on Hippuran(tm); typed copies of published papers on anatomy of paraurethral glands, by Huffman, 1948, and on diverticula of the urethra, by Davis, 1960; extensive bibliographic notes
  - "Renal tuberculoma and tuberculous perinephric abscess", 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    two typescripts of article by JAB and Hobart L. Boyd, one as submitted and one edited, plus receipt acknowledgment by Journal of Urology; reprint, Journal of Urology, 53(2):265-268, Feb. 1945; mounted figures
  - "Study of experimental urinary calculi", 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    typescripts & reprints of a series of three articles by JAB, James G. Wilson, Alice D. Leahy (authors in differing order), published in Journal of Urology as follows: "I. Methods for producing and preventing calculus formation in the bladder and urethra of albino rats," 54:503-515, Dec. 1945; "II. Quantitative microchemical spectrographic, and citric acid analysis of albino rat caculi, with a preliminary apatite report," 54:516-524, Dec. 1945; "III. Persistence of stone-forming tendency in estrogen-treated male rats and its relation to diet," 56:151-158, Aug. 1948 with cover letters and other correspondence; correspondence re. chemical analysis of the stones; several illustrations, one mounted; reprint of Thompson, JAB, et al. paper; over twenty reprints by various authors, some with presentation notes; see also Box 2-F42 for another copy of paper no. II
  - "The role of bilateral orchiectomy in the treatment of carcinoma of the prostate gland", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    subtitle: "A report of 82 cases"; reprint by W.W. Scott & JAB, Bulletin of the New York Academy of Medicine, 21(6):307-318, Jun. 1945; notes
  - "Continuity of the fasciae lining the abdomen, pelvis, and spermatic cord", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    typescript and reprint of article by Charles E. Tobin, JAB, and John C. Wells, Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 83:575-596, Nov. 1946; one illustration; see also Box 4-F4, F6, & F7
  - "Endocrinologic studies on the prostate gland in the male rabbit. II. The response of intraocular prostatic implants to estrogens in thecom- pletely prostatectomized animal, intact and castrate", 1947 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    reprint & three typed versions of article by Boris Krichesky & JAB, Journal of Urology, 58(2):114-124, Aug. 1947; extensive notes; translations of German literature; one reprint; correspondence re. manuscript; original mounted illustrations & their galley proof; see also Box 1-F15 & F16
  - "Endocrinologic studies on the prostate gland in the male rabbit. III. The response of intraocular autotransplants of prostate tissue to estrone and to diethylstilbesterol dipropionate in the intact and castrated completely prostatectomized animal (Box 1, Folder 33)
    two drafts of an article by JAB, Boris Krichesky, and Charles Slato (sp.?); for numbers I and II in the series, see Box1-F15 & F32, respectively; no indication that no. III was ever published; also extensive notes, one reprint, translations from earlier German writers
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    notes, one reprint
  - "Repair of hypospadias with free inlay skin graft", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    reprint and typed drafts of article by Forrest Young & JAB, Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 86:439-451, Apr. 1948; reprint has pencilled annotations re. additional follow-up data; also a letter mentioning the article and asking to visit JAB's department; extensive notes; correspondence re. attempt to find portrait of G abriel Nové-Josserand for the article; two reprints by David M. Davis
  - Presentation [?] on hypospadia repair procedures, [1948?] (Box 1, Folder 36)
    one and one-half page typed summary bearing the note "aided in part by the Dr. Henry C. Buswell Memorial," plus bibliography; extensive notes
  - "A comparative follow-up study of the therapeutic value of bilateral orchiectomy in the treatment of carcinoma of the prostate gland", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    reprint & some of the illustrations of an article by W.W. Scott & JAB, Journal of Urology, 60(4):604-611, Oct. 1948
  - Urological Postgraduate Seminar, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    transcript of lectures sponsored by the Northeastern Section, American Urological Association, Univ. of Buffalo, Jan. 3-8, 1949; JAB presented: "Congenital anomalies of the kidney," and "Continuation of anomalies of the lower urinary tract"
  - "Anatomic and clinical re-evaluation of Camper's, Scarpa's, and Colles' fasciae", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    reprint of article by Charles E. Tobin and JAB, Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 88:545-559, May 1949; see also Box 4-F6 & F7
  - "Chronic prostatitis and seminal vesiculitis", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    reprint of section by JAB in: A Textbook of Surgery, ed by Frederick Christopher. 5th edition. Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders, 1949. pp. 1 287-1291
  - "Radioactive phosphorus (P32) used to study phosphate exchange be-tween urine in the renal pelvis and renal calculi containing phosphate", 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    three typed drafts and reprint of an article by JAB, William F. Neuman, Herbert E. Thompson and Christine Waterhouse, Science, 111(2888):498-499, May 5, 1950; with a cover letter and four photographs mounted on cardboard
  - Genetic hypospadias, 1949-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    reprints of articles by: Forrest Young and JAB, "Preschool age repair of hypospadias with free inlay skin graft," Surgery, 26(3):384- 404, Sep. 1949; John M. Hamilton, 1969; and Norman B. Hodgson,; handwritten and typed notes on patient x-ray movies; a letter of consultation from JAB on a patient x-ray movie study, 1968 [RESTRICTED]
  - Dog reflux studies, x-ray movies, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 2)